this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se radio is
brought to you by the I Triple E
Computer Society I Triple E software
magazine online at computer org slash
software I'm Adam Gordon Bell for
software engineering radio today I have
with me
Burke I guy's the co-founder of ops
genie which is I think now an Alaskan
company and an expert on modern incident
management practices ricotta welcome to
software engineering radio hey thanks so
I wanted to pick your brain a little bit
about you know what is an incident
management process and if I'm a
developer and my organization is trying
to introduce some sort of process what
type of things do I need to know so I
thought a good place to start would be
like what's an incident yeah it's in
there's anything that's unexpected that
disrupts the systems or applications
whatever you're running that unplanned
unexpected why do I need a management
process for that this became more of a
importance or a priority in the later
years as the expectations of the users
and the customers for availability of a
service reliability performance security
increase as well as the the pressure in
the market to innovate and do things
faster and faster like the rate of
change also changed there there might be
an incident that if the organization
reacts fast enough to prevent impact on
the users as well and resolve it before
the customers or users are impacted by
that incident as well so it's often a
race against time and you know as the
developers or the people operating the
the service we want to make sure that we
either mitigate the impacts that as
little as possible or if you know
ideally prevent the impact from
happening by responding on time finding
the problem and resolving as quickly as
possible
so that's interesting so if we act fast
enough we might actually prevent there
from being any impact what what common
causes of incidents DC by far the most
common cause of incidence is change and
the rate of change increased as I'm sure
you know in the recent years with all
the you know the DevOps and all the
paradigms that came with it and the rate
of change is really the the biggest
driver of incidents in the in our
systems and so that would make me think
that the way to prevent incidents is
slow down change the approach it is a
common approach but the research kind of
indicates that it isn't true so the the
that's actually typical friction point
in in organizations the developers would
like because business wants things to
change or you know new things to come
out as fast as possible there will
approach tries to push those things and
the operations folks are typically
resisting change because the change is
what interests use all the you know
instability problems to the system and
in the traditional enterprise there's a
major friction between Devin offs they
push in different directions and in the
last decade the the DevOps movement
attempts to address that by having the
changing all the the paradigm and
developers and operations folks working
together breaking that silo so that that
negative dynamic is not there so there
are different ways to solve that if you
make frequent changes small changes you
minimize the the sort of the rate of
failure or when there is a failure you
can address it very quickly because as
you make frequent changes each change is
very small yeah if I can take the other
side because it sounds interesting yeah
to me it sounds like that's actually
making more changes right you're saying
change causes incidents but now you know
instead of releasing every week we're
gonna release every day that sounds like
more change to me more places where
things can break yeah that's where
that's where it's it's somewhat you know
intuitively you go the other direction
initially but it again what we find
ourselves as well that when the change
is small you kind of accept that some
some portion of that will cause a
problem but you can address that so the
typically in this they wants to look at
the change failure rate how often the
change causes a problem the others the
metric is the how long it takes you to
restore it so like you try to reduce the
number of failures but also like how
long it takes you to find it time to
determine and fix the problem
the unexpected maybe thing is that when
you do fewer changes the changes are
like you do one change but it has a lot
of things in it because there will of
course keep developing right so like
it's actually not one change like you
just have one big change that has
hundred changes in it and if that breaks
something it's typically very difficult
to find what it is so the mean time to
repair keeps getting longer and longer
and you know you can't prevent the
customers impact in those cases there
are a number of practices that dev teams
came up with in the recent years one of
them is like feature flagging cannery
stuff like so you can kind of a roll out
test and with the subset of users before
you roll out to everybody else but the
key is really they know exactly what
they've done and how they would detect a
problem like if it didn't work so the
the time to awareness of the problem and
the ability to dissect what the problem
is troubleshoot is as much higher
because there will a bird knows what
they've done and because the change is
smaller the number of options that you
have to check is not that high either so
they can quickly revert the change or
fix it or whatever so it's a interesting
that the body of research indicates that
these type of frequent change makes the
system more stable and not not less
which is a interesting concept yeah
definitely can you define feature
flagging and canary builds and then
maybe explain how they do
sure let's say you have a hundred
thousand users that use your system and
you make it change and you expose all of
them if there is a failure it's going to
impact everybody like so you have a
significant problem versus the cannery
one you can put a cohort of thousand
people and enable the feature for them
first if there is a problem you still
had a problem but only 1% of your users
got impacted by that so that's you know
I think in the core of it the fact that
you just accept that there will be a
problem and no amount of testing in
advanced in the lab and so on will tell
you like it will make it sure that in
production and you deploy it's gonna
work so you're deploying in production
but containing it to the blast radius to
a small radius so that if there's a
problem you roll it back but the impact
is you know much smaller than what it
would be and the future flagging is sort
of a similar concept that you can you
sort of a separate deployment of the
features from enablement of the feature
like you deploy the feature and then
slowly turn it on for people using the
feature flag or customers like you know
in SAS we have customers as tenants so
you can enable for one ten and five
tenants you know and if it goes okay but
you look at metrics and you enable for
more people so it's a more controlled
approach to handle that the inevitable
like there will be something wrong I
think the approach to assume that there
won't be incidents and try to prevent
incidents proven to be like it's you you
lose that battle so it's better to be
prepared for it like that this will
happen and if it does happen what do you
do like so one part is to have a process
in incident management process that's
ready so you don't have to think of
anything like you know exactly what's
going to happen you get to the right
person as quickly as possible like
escalates
you know when how long you gonna wait to
escalate you know which person do you go
depending on time of day if you have
24/7 services in different continents
you can
which the business hours and wherever
like all that who are we going to tell
otherwise to stakeholders you know the
business users or maybe legal you know
the communications depending on how it
is there are a lot of decisions and the
the incident management process of
preparing all that in advance like if
this type of incident happens you know
exactly what's going to happen so you're
not scrambling during the incident
you kind of prepare for in advance in
peacetime is the is one of the aspects
you mitigate limiting the time time it
takes to resolve problems and peace
times I like this metaphor where if
there's no incidents where a peace and
if there is during peacetime the less
you know trouble you have during more
time so to speak I think this is the
terminology the firefighters used like
the they have a pretty mature incident
management process like we'll be taking
a lot of what what they've done there
that is a book on this by a few
Alzheimer's firefighters that took that
and sort of are going through the they
have a practice that they actually teach
organizations how to do this and they
have a book on this like that you know
some of the terminology that you know I
took from from there kind of makes sense
easy to understand that's super
interesting well I want to go back to
something you said about not focusing on
on not having incidents so I would
assume that our goal would be that we
are able to reduce it so that we never
actually have to run this process but
what you're saying seems to indicate
that's maybe not the way yeah it's again
maybe it's not as the intuitive thing
that we did find out that it is not the
way what our selves as well as the
customer so the when we looked at the
data just to see the companies
organizations that have incidents and
respond to them let's say you know
almost daily and and this is the part
like the incident is not always a
already impact but you have some in
advance like something is gonna break or
you have redundancy I'm one of the
redundant site is gone like you're
customers still work but you are exposed
and so on the companies that have
incidents frequently are much more
mature in their how they handle it
the ones that don't have any anything
and there's an alert that something is
broken about the incident but they only
get like one couple of alerts or months
they're much more like sluggish because
there is no muscle in the organization
to how to how to respond and you know
cuz no one really knows what's gonna
happen like they try to scramble figure
out like who to tell what to put in a
communications to the customers and so
on where is this the ones that have
things and respond and hopefully prevent
they have that muscle like our internal
things get quite a lot of alerts based
on things that can like daily we kind of
error on the side of caution because
it's a really critical service the
service we don't have
and it needs to be very highly available
because other organizations rely on it
to tell them so the the team and the
person that's on call during the day
they get you know alerts respond to it
so they know almost muscle memory what
to do like when there is an and also it
reduces we find that stress level like
the it's not a very odd sort of a Black
Swan type of when the event that it
happens you know what to do so it's a
like a calmer situation than a like when
it's a very rare kind of a thing to do
because we find that the fear of the
incident especially for Hong Kong people
was causing significant stress and like
the someone is on cold you know you
think that they will be woken up when
there's a problem but like they have
sleep problems like the all these things
that even though there is no incident
there is an impact on their lives
because especially if they're not
accustomed to it so in our internal
process it takes about almost a year for
some for an engineer to be night on-call
alone like when there's a problem so we
we get them they are on call during the
day for quite a while so when there are
others around and you know they're not
alone they can get help quite quickly to
be
the confidence level and as they do that
at some point between you know 6 to 12
months they become your night on call
and there is much more confident and the
stress level goes down significantly in
that sense because they have their you
know gone through that motion many times
before
that's an interesting transition to the
kind of developer perspective if I join
ups Jeanne I haven't worked someplace
before with the incident process do I
start an incident what do I do if some
service that I own is acting up yeah so
there's maybe two different ways of
working on this one that we find again
the more mature organizations that have
higher demands on reliability and
security have a lot of automation so we
have a ton of monitoring systems
external internal that generate alerts
basically so the automated systems when
there's a problem or there may be a
problem they generate alerts and those
alerts go to the on-call person to
investigate so at that point there might
not be an incident like it might be
preliminary but if they think there is
an incident they initiate the process in
some cases you know is there incident
it's very clear then you automatically
start innocent process as well so in
others organizations incidents come from
users reporting something right like the
external and then you start things in
the process and start bringing the
people and so it's either automated
through the monitoring systems or as a
human initiates the incident process so
I get an alert it says I don't know this
database is at 99 percent or something
yeah yeah and then I make a call so what
do I do if I decide it's an incident and
how do I make that call and that's the
part at least in our case I think you
have to give the confidence that it's
okay to like if they believe that you
know pull the lever so to speak and the
first thing they have to do is to
understand the impact of the incident
like is it a something small is it
something big
one team multi team so like depending on
the level of impact there is a
difference in the process and the
organization the team's typically set
that up like if it's a priority one
incident the impacting customers there
is a incident process that is different
than it impacts you know like one
percent of the users and it's you know
they can do their stuff but it's you
know it's a UI problem for example like
there is a different level and the first
thing that don't go person does is to
assess that like is it something that
can wait till the morning you know you
don't know it has to be all hands on
deck and there's a different based on
the priority they said on the incident
it would trigger a different process and
that person doesn't really have to know
everything about the process they just
need to set the priority and in our case
like a the optionee system would trigger
a different flow like if it is a all
hand on hands on deck maybe it's three
four different teams you need someone
from each and it would start a
notification process for each of the
teams and track the process each of them
coming to a zoom session for example to
address it in other layer less priority
it's maybe it's just one team one person
if they can isolate what service the
problem is then you just add that team
as a responder to the incident and that
teams instant process kicks in to
determine the crew from that team should
be notified and how it should escalate
and so on how do I actually pull the
flag adopts genie I'm sure it varies but
yeah what do you do yeah you can if
you're in slack you can say you know
create incident and that would start
there are a bunch of different ways
Orion there's like a main reaction that
you create incident and you can manually
create a new incident so it could be a
fresh incident it could be like can also
group number of alerts and I say that
these others are all related to this one
incident so you can have a incident
process and associate those alerts to it
so that the people coming in can can see
that because it's not all it's typically
not one alert like when something
significant happens you know we have a
bunch of different monitoring system
most of our most organizations do they
all start sending alerts and it's pretty
noisy like if it's if it's a bigger one
you may
zooom so yeah I start an incident and it
starts to zoom room and I jump in it and
what happens other people join or not
all incidents are handled through video
conferencing it's typically reserved to
more higher priority higher impact stuff
like that's the you know incident if you
set priority one maybe you initiated
zoom conference kind of a thing if it's
priority to me might be just chat that
you handle through the chat system the
different teams do different setups
there but that's typically done in
peacetime to be ready when it happens I
think there's an internet I start it
yeah so it starts a slack channel I'm
not sure of like two things first of all
is who to bring in and second of all is
how to figure out what the impact is
what should I do next it depends on your
internal systems are in some some ways
but our approach is that option kind of
a provides concept of services so each
team can define the services they have
if they're providing and other teams can
create dependencies that I use this team
service so that you kind of see like
that in our root cause investigation
like you asked early like what is the
cause of the incidents and that I
mentioned the changes and there is a
flavor of it that if it's not a change
that you introduce it's typically a
change that someone else Institute that
like your service depends on their
service and they have a problem
impacting you so that's what you're
trying to see like where is that you're
trying to isolate the problem like to
determine the right response like the
who who you gonna need depending on what
services are impacted if you if you have
put some work on it like the if this
services impacted you know a priority
one incident on this service would
trigger a response time that I need
people from these these these teams and
then you they will get notified into one
place and at that point you are
investigating like we do provide tools
like for different services incidents
you can run actions to trigger like the
most common things that you wanna it
the website is still up right like you
can check that it's a maybe the DNS
resolution to see like run a traceroute
to see like how the network stuff is you
can put those into the incident in
typically the organizations that are
more mature have run books basically
because you want even the junior people
to be able to go through the first steps
to understand like where it is rum books
typically have the actions that do this
first do that next kind of things and
they start from who to bring in if the
system doesn't support it that would be
manually in the in the round book
progressively they go into a more
investigative steps like okay run these
commands check whether this is working
or like the typical things to do but I
think you know those steps are very
useful in identifying the right course
of action in terms of what should the
response should be the conflict is often
because there's you know like lots of
these things happen so you want to wake
everybody up so to speak if it is a real
problem but you don't want to wake
everybody up if it isn't a problem so
you get that sort of tugging in both
directions and that type of a set up you
know this is the wrong book this is how
it decides it reduces again the pressure
on the people who are responding initial
first responders so to speak to the to
the incident to to call like you don't
want to blame them for for doing that if
they if they need to pull it and that's
where you like the more context you give
to them and empower them to identify
because if they don't have that
information it's they become sort of a
you know don't have the tools to make
the decision and no matter what they do
like there's an implication to it like
you you you you don't want them to
hesitate to call people because they're
you know afraid of what people will say
and so on yeah it seems like a hard
balance to find yes yeah it is harder
for the junior ones as well
yeah because they don't want to wake
everybody up yeah so I see that the
database is really high usage so I
started an incident I go to the rum book
the rum book says you know check ok
three services use this are they up and
it's like oh yeah they're up and maybe
then the usage starts to fall down so
what do I do is that is at the end for
that particular incident like maybe the
impact is is minor or if the impact is
minor typically again that depending on
when it is that like if it's to work
hours you may solve that the each team
handles differently like I think one of
the things that is impactful is that
there are low frequency high impact
incidents like when those happen they
don't happen very often but when it
happens it makes them use so to speak
you know the if it is a big company and
there is lots of high frequency low
impact once all that spectrum is really
necessary to to have peaceful
development time the developers are
impacted by the like one of the things
that we've just done like showing the we
call the unplanned work you know that
anytime you're working on incidents
you're doing unplanned work and it
impacts your plan work which you had a
scene as JIRA is you know and when you
are planning the next sprint or
something like that if you don't know
the level of unplanned work it's often
the cause of friction and it also like
messes up with your planning like
because you think is this many hours so
that we try to combine the unplanned
work like I'm much time the team
collectively spent in the last sprint so
that you can kind of try to gauge like
is it going up or down like is your
unplanned time percentage-wise overall
is it going up so at UPS Jeanne what
level of unplanned would you feel is a
problem I would say 20% is pretty high
if you if you continuously have that we
try to reduce that quite lower than that
I think we are somewhat fortunate in the
sense that it's pretty clear that this
service needs to be reliable so like I
you know we don't have to justify it
right like it's yeah it's not if it's
not a reliable business is no longer
there I find it is harder for some of
my colleagues friends you know like do I
build a new feature or invest more into
you know cleaning up the code to reduce
technical debt and so on
it's not always easy so like that's
that's what we're trying to help with
like in the product to show like how
much time you're spending because it's
often intuitive oh I'm spending too much
time but you can't quantify the impact
of that like if you can invest and
reduce the planned time you know a few
percentage points like it opens up
additional capacity later that you can
invest in development and the worst I
think when when people see the unplanned
time is kind of creeping up like it's
you know on the way upwards is down it's
it's more of our like which way it's
going like if it's going at least you're
you you know you can see the light at
the end of the tunnel if it's going down
if it's going up like you're gonna be in
bigger trouble so it's more than the
number it's probably the trend of like
which direction is heading is is more
important probably for most themes it
sort of damages the morale as well and
so like becomes a vicious circle like it
really is key to like nipple and early
on and make sure that it doesn't creep
up so just being aware of that like how
much unplanned time you have spends
every cycle I think is super useful for
teams to not to get into that like
vicious cycle so to speak got it so you
said that there are certain sort of high
frequency low impact incidents that may
be happening could you give some
examples getting people's attention in
the cloud infrastructure is designed to
fail right like that was the biggest
thing like we used to design all these
like super resilient stuff and I assume
that they will never fail or at least
try that versus like you know you're
running it over this cloud like stuff
fails all the time so you're you get
five hundreds or the queue starts
building up because there's some kind of
problem somewhere and it starts routing
around that so every time you know NSPS
queue for example it builds up is an
alert sometimes it's
you know resolves because additional
resources are automatically provisioned
sometimes it doesn't so there are some
automated ways or many ways to handle
the problems like maybe one of the
servers went down and you got some bunch
of 500 but they take a reach right and
going through that one school of thought
is like you don't have to worry about
those till there is a customer impact
mm-hmm I find that if you can get away
with it that's the you know easier
approach right like if if you don't have
to react to problems until there is a
customer impact which you know your
business requirements might allow that
that is a lower burden on there were
present operations people we can't
afford that like you know if he had
multiple outages within the same year
that you know you would see the
financial impact of it directly in our
business so like we we do a lot more
alerting early on before that the impact
like this queue is climbing up or the
number of retries go up like what is
going on is that something that's gonna
fail if you don't address or so like
each of those create generate an alert
and someone responds to it to monitor
what's happening to prevent an outage
prevent the customer impacting incidents
so there's quite a bit of those but you
know the muscle to like figure out what
might be causing that is something that
only happens with it like that's why we
call like six to twelve months depending
on the seniority of the developers to
get that because they know if this queue
is building up is typically something
there right like or we're sending text
messages and it to be Lia interface is
acting up like that's what's causing
this those type of things you can write
them down but like you're not gonna able
to read them like when there's an
incident so it's a you know it has to be
like almost memory almost - in some ways
and if you get there even if it's middle
of the night you go get some of the
alerts and SS this is a big problem
priority one incident go or you know you
can snooze it till the morning and then
the
morning it would notify you again a like
there was an incident and so and if it's
still active you can take a look at the
end or whoever is on call at that time
can take a look into it so it's a
assessment then the right level of
response is really what they need to
figure out and the experience is the
only way to gain that it's interesting I
think that I heard you say something
like so we have this queue and if the
work backs up we want to spin up more
nodes and maybe we could automate that
but if we automate away all of our minor
incidents then nobody knows how to run
an incident so you actually yeah that is
exactly what what we see which is
interesting so like and and the
automation in two ways like one people
don't have the experience and the - the
automation has problems - like so that
the more complex that automations get
like you know the most problematic
instance that we you know I had seen
there was some kind of automation that
went haywire like more more so than the
actual problems like so it's a you know
what's an example of automation going
awry one of things was like the retiring
you know like ramping down after build
up like you added nodes and capacity and
when it was doing that it messed things
up so there was no instance left that
was accessible so the you know the
process to ramp I mean right now it's
like AWS has far more stable systems for
auto scaling early on we had our own
mechanisms so it would scale up scale up
was tested much more than this scale
down so during the scale down to logic
got messed up and took the systems out
of the balancer and like they were no
longer it looked like they were there
but they weren't serving traffic so we
had you know sort of a semi outage there
like it was the you know one instance
left had to handle all the loads so like
I mean this is code as well and it's a
very hard to test code if you're writing
automation like all the edge cases is
hard to test so that's why when a cloud
provider like a double yes
as those things they generally gone
through a lot of you know lots of
customers using all the edge cases and
stuff when you do your own automation I
think there's a high higher degree of
risk in there because it's hard to find
all the edge cases and test them like
it's not necessarily software like they
have to fail in certain ways the chaos
engineering discipline is trying to sort
of address that like the there is a
growing in the last few years
discipline around chaos engineering that
essentially you introduce failures into
the system regularly to make sure that
the system handles that so if you have
you know fail over multiple regions all
those type of things whatever happens if
I remove one servers five servers call
data center like available to zone if
you're doing those again it builds
muscle to do that and I've seen
customers even do sort of like packet
level ones one of my companies I'm
involved with have software that
introduces you know the delay like the
if this service gets overwhelmed and it
starts looks loading and slower what is
the impact of that on the other services
so like you know it introduces a delay
on the response of that and then you
kind of observe what is happening right
like with the micro services the
interdependency and is increasing a lot
so you're testing all this in production
really is the only way to do it because
you have the actual loads and actual
data in there to be able to see it so we
are evolving but I think the complexity
of the systems ends the speed of change
like it's going faster than we can adapt
our processes and the the disciplines
like all this stuff is fairly new to to
tackle all this complexity like how do
we deal with this how do we because you
know micro systems essentially or micro
services the complexity is moving to the
production you know it's all in the
production like as opposed to in the
code like where
have debuggers and like we have tools in
complex application when some all of it
but when it's all in pieces it is a
distributed monolith in some ways and
there's like all these unexpected
interactions between the systems that
you can only tease out by interjecting
some of the failures so I think that
will grow in time as you know again
maturity level right like you the
organization's typically start from like
when something happens I want to make
sure that someone is aware like that's
the first step yeah that's where I've
seen II started like that was the you
know 7 years ago how do we ensure that I
can sleep and you know I know that the
system is gonna wake me up but then like
ok you wake you up and you don't know
anything about the system you're not
gonna be able to do much so providing
context around the the incident similar
ones like from the past
taking a look collaboration like finding
the right person you know it grows in
time but most organizations are still
fairly new to this the incident staff
management process if you typical
organization will tell you when you say
incident management like what do you
think of they will think of the I told
ITSM type incidents which is really the
user reporting it like the user calls
them ok I can't get to the finance
application or it doesn't work whatever
and they're you know you open up a
ticket to escalate to somebody and like
they eventually you know take a look at
it the urgency level is very different
than like the I can't afford downtime
I must instrument instrument my
application and monitor forming outside
so that like when there is a problem I
get that to the right person which is
typically you want to get to the
developer responsible for that part of
the application because they are the
best equipped to assess the problem and
solve the problem as opposed to a
generic ops person that you know you
have hundreds of applications in an
enterprise so I think that in itself is
a is a change as well yeah that the
developer is the person to talk to have
you found that to be a hard call
change for people to make yeah it is it
is very hard I think this part of the
cultural change that there were ups
movements it tries to make it easier you
know like how how to make that change
but it is very difficult the idea in
this case is that whoever is building it
you build that you'll run it whatever
you know there are number of different
ways to address it but is the person the
best equipped to solve the problem and
because you want to minimize the time to
restore you want to find the best person
as quickly as possible so the developer
becomes much more critical in the
process like in most organizations today
traditionally the incident management is
organized to minimize the amount of work
done by higher skill people it's not
organized around time it's more like so
you have a first level support may
create the tickets if they can solve it
second level third level so you have you
know I caused by quality that people
that you can use elsewhere so you don't
want them to just to incident so you try
to protect them yeah and that paradigm
completely changed now you say like it's
optimized around time like I want to go
straight to the person that knows the
best so that they can solve it as fast
as possible that is very difficult
change because rightly it's it puts a
lot more demand on the developers and
not every developer is you know there's
different life styles that like you know
being on call is a not a easy thing you
know that especially if it's not done
right if you're on called one week out
of three weeks or four weeks or
something like that which we've seen
that's a lot like you know and
especially if the system is not stable
and you get notified like you know you
get alerts night it is a problem so like
there is all kinds of things you can do
to reduce that but there's gonna be some
extra burden so I've seen all kinds of
pushback and the change but the you know
there is some options but not really
that many like the geographical
distribution helps like if you have
teams in Europe a new Asia and US you
minimize the of our time so like the
teams can pass on like a passing is
fortunate in that sense like we have
teams in California in Australia as well
as you know we are in Turkey so like you
can kind of a pass on the baton for the
who's gonna take on the incident which
you know it helps but even with that
like not every team has members in
different locations so within your team
you might have to be on call and if
you're on call we can't leave how more
like you have to walk around with your
computer or whatever it is like it's not
a if you have inside if you like if
you're going to a job knowing that's the
requirement is different than your
company is going to a transformation is
now you're expected to do all this I
find the organization's have a lot more
trouble doing that transition to the
existing cultures right like because
it's it is different that before you
would do it then you pass it on like
eco-home versus like you you're not
responsible for the operation of that
having said that I also find that there
is nothing like being the one on call
when there is something going wrong to
motivate you that you know you better
like it's basically that responsibility
and awareness doesn't come naturally if
you're not the one and I always like
pushed the managers to be on call as
well like it's like I don't care that
you can't fix anything like you have to
be woken up and be present to appreciate
like when you know we're talking about
the priority of the you know investing
in reliability versus like features to
make the right decision you really need
everyone to feel the share the pain so
to speak like once I've seen something
explode then when they're saying we
should build this new feature I'll be
thinking whoa wait wait I don't want to
be paged again sadly yes sadly like if
you
not the one waking up it doesn't make
the same impact like you know it's like
we lived through this internally like
it's a like you really appreciate why it
is important like the optionee team has
this concept it's not special to us this
definition of done that like after you
dry to code then you run the tests and
the a peer reviewer would ask bunch of
questions like what about this did you
think of this and stuff like this so
that you get to definition like they're
done by yes like we've looked at all
that because the cost of not doing that
is someone waking an outfit that you
know nighttime or uncle being much more
painful and you appreciate more as a
developer it's just if you are the one
experiencing in the first firsthand
that's like yeah if you know if you
don't pay attention to quality you know
you're gonna give me impacted the
friction typically is with the
management you know like the that is
making decisions on like where to where
to put the time so that's why I like one
of the techniques is like you know you
have to have a incident manager and one
of the managers have to wake up like
when this happens even if people all
they're doing is you know taking notes
it's fine and that that helps with the
empathy I think to decide like where we
put our time and effort next that's
that's a battle-hardened cultural tip
make the managers on call yes yes so if
I'm a developer and join Ops genie or
wherever like so what's the expectations
how often am I on call what are their
expectations when I'm on call we've
settled with a system that works really
well I think and you are after the first
couple months you are on call from you
in your team during the day we call it
where concept of day on call so you you
know within a month or two your day on
call which means that you're getting
alerts you have to figure out what's
happening and then address the problem
but that's sort of a
trains you in the sense and in that
sense you only need to know your teens
like whatever the services that your
team owns like that domain in time you
are expected to learn other domains
because our night on calls are expected
to like we don't have a night on call
for each team the night on call is
responsible for the entire system which
means they need to understand enough to
isolate where the problem is and bring
the right team from that and that's a
you know higher degree of sophistication
that the person needs and that's
typically why it takes at least six
months to get there often nine months or
up to a year then the reason we do that
with that is we have I think in our team
like about fifteen people were I don't
call qualified which means that you are
not on call very frequently like it gets
in you know once in three four months
one week out over three four months
lower if you can't do that then it's
like often more on caller we find
problems with that if you're on call
like every week out of a month or you
know like too frequently it is harder to
do so we opted up with this system that
it takes time to get the person there
but when they're there they are on call
at nighttime but not very frequently
because they know the entire system and
we shared the on call so we have like
two different you know we have an SE
ryeong call and a sort of an application
product phone call person as opposed to
each team each of the eleven teams that
we have having on call and that someone
being able to address multiple domains
made it less frequent and then this like
compounds to many different things like
for this to work you really need to have
low turnover so we you know like we have
loft turnover so we can if let me you
know kind of optimize for that like we
don't want people to you know if you're
getting developers in and out like this
model wouldn't work so it you know
encourages to you as the organization to
invest more into into the you know
keeping the developers longer and and
should they have the right tools and so
on so it can change the entire dynamics
of the organization to be able to handle
like the uncle in an organization has
implications beyond what you might
initially think like how the you know
everything from compensation to you know
how you organize the teams and so on
gets impacted by this when you have
always on 24/7 critical services to
support interesting if I'm on call I'm
the night on call you know something
happens and I track it down to some you
know some service change and some
something else didn't change yeah should
I be you know opening up my IDE and
trying to make extensive changes to to
address things no I mean if it's in that
level you probably first need help like
you know you shouldn't be doing it
yourself but we typically go for the
restoration of the service as opposed to
fixing the problem so it's often can it
be rolled back if it is something to it
like if it's a recent change and that's
the big layer much lower risk kind of a
thing that fix he almost never fix it at
that time unless there is no other way
to do it that's why I like you you want
to make a change during the day and
observe like everything is working if
it's something new the hardest wants to
handle are when you're making a change
that is not reversible like you're
changing the schema data structure so
you can't just roll back the code mm-hmm
that those are hard so you don't want
them to break right I'm like if that
happens I think it is a it is quite hard
to handle but often roll back to a
previous stuff is you know fairly
straightforward we have slack commands
for all those like the how to you know
do those things they can typically run
few commands and restore the service and
then you know later on we can look into
what went wrong so it's often like
restoration of service takes precedence
over fixing what the problem is that's
not asking too much I think like you
know under pressure coding is it's for
movies I think how about people that
people to do
so the the cheat sheet for for being on
call is make sure your manager is on
call as well and they're just always hit
rollback let's go
right yeah I think I basically say like
whoever makes decisions you want them to
feel the like what is it like with a
high pressure incident when you know you
have thousands of customers impacted it
is I mean it messes up the person so
like you don't want anyone individually
shoulder that you want people to as well
as you know like not just the managers
but the peers and so opportunity has
always been very very good at that like
when there's something you typically
like you push a button and there are you
know four or five people whether they're
on call or not jumping and if it is
serious to prevent the outage it really
depends on the expectation on the
service like it's all about business
requirements like if it's not if you can
live with it till the morning don't
obviously but you know we have
increasingly more and more services like
ours that customers have that cannot
afford downtime so organizations are
trying to adapt to like how to operate
without burning people one of the
organization's I worked in in the past
with that they had an operator that was
responsible for getting to the right
person as opposed to our software doing
it and he said basically like so what do
you do you call like I go you know I
look and then like I call and we you
know we looked at the records and like
he was calling John you know there were
four people in the team and 70% of the
time it was John that was cold like well
why is this well John didn't yell yell
at the guy before night so he was a nice
guy so they just kept calling John you
know the other guys were you know cranky
like he at nighttime whatever so and
especially if it was a false alarm they
like they were not happy so they
gravitated toward this one person right
like so it's not fair that you know John
was a nice guy so he'll at times he got
called a lot more than the other people
so yeah there's a lot of
unwritten procedures and stuff that
builds around this because of the high
stress nature of that some of the
managing with a software in a equitable
way takes that like the after using the
software it says I wanna notify the
database team they don't decide like who
in the database team the database team
decides who that night and how it
escalates and so it takes off the
pressure on the person who needs to
raise the belt so to speak to notify
people it helps quite a lot yeah so it
makes sense to have all this planned out
peacetime as you call it to figure out
who yeah who gets called during what
times yeah so what do you do after the
incident how do you learn from this yeah
so post-mortems is it's commonly called
or better name maybe post incident
review or analysis is the you know we're
trying to move to those like less morbid
names on that that processor is using
the wartime peacetime and that's right
the terminology is quite dramatic in
this area like every incident is really
a huge opportunity to learn if you have
the right culture which is you know like
this you may hear that blameless post
mortems so instead of you know focusing
on whose fault it was to like
identify the systemic issues like the
what caused it even if it was someone
push this button like why did they push
that button like it's not it's often
easier to push the blame onto a person
then you know tackle the systemic issues
so the post-mortem is like you know
there are different ways I've seen
companies you know five why is there as
a method used in Atlassian like keep
asking questions to where it is our
software also tries to facilitate this
you know I can generate something that
takes all the information that happens
during the incident like when the alert
came like when was the the conference
started you know who was in the
conference how long they spent as time
in there so that you can
get a sense and all the like different
milestones that people enter during the
incident becomes a record in the post
incident review but then you know
obviously people still need to talk
about like why that happened and so on
so in our world you know Atlassian world
I've seen you would generate the report
and publish into confluence and the rest
of the work can be done with comments
they're people adding stuff and there
might be issues too like as you are
saying like you know instead of fixing
that like after the incident that there
are changes to be made and the JIRA
issues will be created that linked from
the post incidents review to the G ratio
so that instant managers can trace that
to make sure that they are resolved in a
timely manner so in mature organizations
this process post incident review is a
significant process like it's a whole
workflow that needs to happen with
people different teams participating it
there is a good code from all spa that
one of the people who are you know sort
of a leaders in this space about like
one of the ways you can track the
maturity is judging from how many
non-technical people attend the post
insular reviews like the attend or
participate right so like if the
managers or the sales whatever like just
not the engineers but the other people
the more they get involved like it says
signal that organization is actually
learning from the that and the
participating which which I find in
personal experience true as well the
it's typically if it just stays
technical it's easy to like it's a this
technology is buggy and that's why it
happens I feels like it you know you can
pigeonhole and move on it's often
learnings are diminished in that type of
attitude so it's like you try to make it
more as open as possible is one of the
best practices I think like the or and
comprehensive to learn from that it's an
opportunity that should not be missed
to mitigate from the risk of happening
again
what comes out of this incident review
process like if I've done this well
what's the value so it's typically you
know there's a report there is a follow
up actions that if it is a bug it's
obvious that you would have a follow of
action to fix the bug but there are also
actions that you know typically
addresses the resiliency like this
happens it will look at why did it take
us half an hour to identify the problem
right like the how do we reduce that why
did it take 20 manners to gather the
right people like the process
improvements so those are the follow of
actions that the report and the the
actions that comes through that gets
widely I think disseminated in mature
organizations irie quite a bit the
postings and analysis reports that teams
that come up with again that you would
learn quite a bit but from what other
teams are doing as well because you can
find single point of failures there you
can find process inefficiencies if there
are people you know burnout or the like
you can find those things identify and I
think the they're a bunch of actions to
address those things the underlying
structural issues to prevent often in
our world again this is different
in the past the same incidents would
happen repeatedly okay so you can you
can have this first level second level
third level the first level support
this is the same incident and now I know
what to do and I fix that in our world
the same isn't almost never happens
twice because you something happens and
then you go fix the bug the next one
will be different what will be the same
is the structural issues that's causing
the the response time how long it takes
to identify the problem those things are
you know stay the same so if you focus
on those like the process issues you
know people are empowered or all those
things that impact that's when you start
making I think gains against how long it
takes to solve or even prevent things
from happening is really that process
that as opposed to like this bug in this
application that bug is fixed it's not
going to happen again
but there's gonna be something else that
will happen I take it if the same
incident is happening and that early
you're probably not taking the right
actions or some yeah if the same thing
is happening again that that's a much
bigger problem like that means that
you're not addressing the underlying
issue for whatever reason and it
sometimes is the you can replace the
technology that easily so it keeps
causing problems but it tells you if you
like we have a lot of reporting tools to
analyze the past incidents alerts to
honored some of those as well look we
are getting a bunch of things from this
technology like whether it's an
application or you know it's some kind
of database or if you know external
service you use whatever it is if you
can gain the insights that's posing you
mean you can prioritize whether you want
to replace or invest more into
stabilizing it that's kind of a part of
the post incidents like these are again
like stuff that you're doing in the
piece time like analyze your data for
insights like what's causing it you know
what is the response time of different
teams like these are all questions we
can ask the data we collect enough
shiney to optimize the process basically
and learn like why why things are
happening you know if same people are
getting notified like you know they're
on call system they might be
underpowered or they don't have enough
senior people that can take the burden
like those are I mean you know there
were offers are hard to recruit and you
want to retain them like if you're
causing burnout like you're hurting
yourself so like any kind of early signs
of those that you can detect because
people sustain the that kind of
punishment for awhile but then they just
quit right like you know so you can't
wait they complain about it not not
every developer complain loudly it's an
important for the management to pay
attention to how the sort of they will
approach health in that sense that are
the process is sustainable in that sense
that you know you not
burdening people what do you think the
biggest mistake is the organization's
make as they're making this transition
to have a process I think its biggest
mistake is the under estimating the the
cultural aspects of it we have a quite a
bit of a tendency to lean on tools as a
solution to this the cultural change is
you know often in almost every part of
the business harder you're expecting
quite a bit I think we are expecting
quite a bit of a change in people
especially if you do those without
involving them into the thought process
like why this is happening how it's
gonna make better and it happens to them
I've seen the biggest problems in the
organizations that someone decides to
adopt DevOps
you know and then like pushes the
organization you're all Devils now then
you know your own call whatever there's
huge problems with that as opposed to
the team sort of reaching to that
conclusion or at least you know even if
it is not fun to do like they appreciate
that it needs to be done that consensus
like building that like the fact that
increased productivity in the sense that
you have less unplanned that the stuff
that we talked about in the beginning
it's on intuitive but it reduces the
unplanned work like all that not
building the consensus in the
organization and the you know involving
the the change necessary
it gets underestimated and then you know
it kind of blows up later that's the
biggest problem that I've seen yeah
there's definitely some unintuitive
aspects of it I was wondering it seems
like you know instant management process
you talked about firefighters like
traditionally this has kind of been the
domain of emergency services yeah so why
is this becoming important in the world
of software yeah I think it's it's part
of the software is eating the world you
know concept right like it's just our
dependency reliance on software is
increasing in a very rapid pace
that makes a lot of sense software is
becoming much more important and there's
lots of places we can learn from so I
know that Atlassian put together
incident management handbook that
probably goes into a lot more details
I'll put a link to that in the show
notes ok thanks so much this has been
great talking to you this is Adam Gordon
belt and thank you for listening to
software engineering radio thanks for
listening the SC radio an educational
program brought to you by Archer police
software magazine for more about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio net to provide
feedback you can comment on each episode
on the website or reach us on LinkedIn
Facebook Twitter or through our slack
channel at SC radio.com you can also
email us at team @ SC - radio net this
and all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under Creative Commons license
2.5 thanks for listening